I have put this program in place for a
reason and that is to better protect the
American
people. And when we find somebody who
may have information regarding an
potential attack on America, you bet
we're going to detain them. And you bet
we're going to question
them because the American people expect
us to find out information,
uh, actionable intelligence so we can
help them, help protect them. That's our
job. So, that was archived footage uh
from the Oval Office of former President
Bush referring to two secret memos in
2005 that authorized extreme
interrogation tactics against terrorist
suspects. As you can see, US policy has
been evolving to where we are for quite
some time. Let's just get right into it.
And I personally want to let's start off
with this question because I spent the
most formative years of my life and
joined special operations command and
the 75th Ranger Regiment. And when I
started to branch more into like human
intelligence collection and got plugged
into the kinetic strike targeting cycle
of drone strikes in Afghanistan
officially. Of course, I knew we were
dropping people who shouldn't have been
dropped. Uh and I was a field
interrogator for a while and we knew
other interrogators that were still like
pretty brutal. I never believed in
negative incentives. Um, it's just not
who I was personally. Uh, you know, and
and there were some reforms after the
torture report came out. Uh, but
basically it was basically just don't
use waterboarding or threaten to use
dogs and don't get caught. Uh my
question that I always like to ask like
when you put the wheels in motion to
blow the whistle on human rights abuses
by US clandestine services, why did you
do it or what did you hope to achieve
and put yourself at such personal risk?
Like I've just met so many guys uh who
either didn't care or were resentful
that they couldn't go even further. So
sure, you know, one of the reasons why I
did it was well, let me back up.
I was the chief of CIA counterterrorism
operations in Pakistan in the immediate
aftermath of 9/11. When I returned to
CIA headquarters in May of 2002, I was
asked if I wanted to be trained in what
they called the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques. I had never
heard that term before. I didn't know
what it meant. And the way it was
explained to me in my mind was clearly
torture.
And I was well read enough to know that
we have the Federal Torture Act of
1946. We have the United Nations
Convention Against to Torture. We have
other laws that that very clearly
delineate what we are allowed to do in
national security custodial
um
interrogations. I declined the training.
I I was the only one of the 14 people
who were approached who declined to be
involved. Um at the same time I was
promoted because I had led the capture
of Abu Zuba who we believed was the
number three in al-Qaeda at the time and
who was the first person to be subject
to
torture.
So I got promoted to be the U executive
assistant to the CIA's deputy director
for operations. And in that position, I
was able to see for one year, I was able
to see literally everything that the CIA
was doing around the world. It was 100%
crystal clear to me that there were a
lot of people inside the CIA who were
opposed to the torture program. People
were writing cables back to headquarters
from the secret site saying, "Whoa, this
is not what I I signed up for. I'm not
going to do this. I want to come home."
That's called a curtailment where you
curtail your overseas assignment. It's a
careerending decision. There were people
who resigned from the secret site. There
were nurses who fainted
uh while watching the torture sessions.
There were doctors from the office of
medical services who would write, "Wait
a minute. Wait a minute. I took an oath
to do no harm, and you want me to be
there to revive this guy after you kill
him so that you can torture him more?
I'm not doing that. So I thought, well,
certainly somebody is going to say
something. After my
tour on the uh executive floor was done,
I went to the United Nations for my
final tour. And then I resigned from the
CIA and I went into the private sector,
still thinking somebody's going to say
something. And then finally in 2007, I
said something to ABC News. My only
regret was that I
left five and a half years on the table.
I learned about the torture in May of
2002. It started on August the 2nd, 2002
and I didn't say anything until December
the 11th,
2007 and I wish I had said something
sooner. Did more than most. Um, what was
the the the source of uh I don't know
your your desire to do that? Because
I've I've known people opposed to the
torture program just for very practical
real politic reasons, you know. It
doesn't work, right? It it doesn't work
and it if it ever comes out, it it
degrades US soft power globally. Yeah,
it very much does. The reason why I felt
so strongly about it is as soon as I
like the the moment that I heard about
it, my response to the senior officer
who approached me was that sounds like a
torture program. Torture is illegal. And
he said, "No, it's not a torture
program. The president signed off on it
and the justice department signed off on
it. It's perfectly legal." And I said,
"I don't know, man. Let me think about
it." So besides asking a a senior
officer for his opinion and his opinion
was quite strongly in opposition to the
program, I started to do my own research
and what I found was and this was very
convincing to me was that in 1945 and
1946 we executed Japanese soldiers who
had waterboarded American PS. That was a
death penalty crime to waterboard
somebody. and we executed several
Japanese soldiers for waterboarding. On
January the 11th,
1968, the Washington Post ran a front
page photograph of an American soldier
waterboarding a North Vietnamese
prisoner. The day that that picture was
published, the Secretary of Defense,
Robert S. McNamera, ordered an
investigation. The soldier was arrested.
He was convicted of torture and he was
sentenced to 20 years at hard labor at
Levvenworth. Besides that, not only is
the US a signatory to the United Nations
Convention Against
Torture, it's the author of the United
Nations Convention Against Torture.
So, if waterboarding somebody was a
death penalty offense or worthy of 20
years at hard labor, and not only did we
feel so strongly about the law here in
the United States, but we made it
international law by writing the UN
Convention, how could it just magically
be be legal in 2002? Just poof, by
magic. Congress never passed any
amendment to the law. We changed. It's
like when Bill Clinton, you know,
disagreed with what the what the
definition of is
is. You can't just pretend that the law
doesn't exist or pretend that you
somehow have the authority to ignore it
because you don't like it. And so that's
why I felt so strongly about it. And and
that's why I felt that the American
people had to write had a right to know
about it. You know, this really is the
definition of an extraordinary
rendition.
Well, I'll let you decide. It could be
just a rendition. Either way, it's
illegal. There's no due process here,
right? This this guy in from Maryland
that has been sent to El Salvador um was
not given due process. He's never been
charged with a crime and nobody's going
to meet with him and he's not going to
be released. And then we have the
president say, "Actually, we would like
to uh finance the building of four or
five more of these 30,000 unit, you
know, super prisons." Well, what the
heck is that? So, is the plan that we
just are doing away with with due
process? Do Americans or US persons,
people who have valid green cards, do
they just no longer have civil rights
and civil liberties? because it sure
looks like that's the road we're taking.
I think so, too. I think they're going
to force the issue all the way to the
Supreme Court. And even then, I'm not
sure that the administration can be
trusted to abide by a Supreme Court
ruling.